Guide to the Martin Shubik Papers, 1947-2009 and undated, bulk 1960-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings and Research Series, 1951-2009 and undated, (59 boxes)
  - Writings by Shubik Subseries, 1952-2008 and undated, (59 boxes)
    - Articles by Shubik, 1952-2008 and undated, (18 boxes)
      - Cowles Foundation Reports (CFR), 1960-2005, (9 boxes)
        - CFDP No. 1202
        - CFDP No. 1253 (drafts, revisions, notes, Santa Fe Working Paper), (2 folders)
        - CFDP No. 1304
        - CFDP No. 1343
        - CFDP No. 1396 (typed manuscript, draft, correspondence), (3 folders)
        - CFDP No. 1413 (final copy with activity report)
        - CFDP No. 1414 (Box 72)
        - CFDP No. 1424 (typed manuscript with revisions, draft with notes, correspondence), (3 folders)
        - CFDP No. 1439 (corrections copy)
        - CFDP Nos. 1455 and 1460 (drafts, notes, no final report), (3 folders)
        - CFDP Unidentified number: Game Theory, Complexity and Simplicity, Part II, 1997
        - Cowles Foundation Report, Nos. 250-359
        - CFR Nos. 363-447
        - CFR Nos. 450-578
        - CFR Nos. 584-731 (Box 73)
        - CFR Nos. 741-1049
    - Books by Shubik Subseries, 1950s-2009 and undated, (34 boxes)
      Contains drafts, correspondence, manuscripts, notes, book reviews and proofs from selected major works by Shubik, including Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, Game Theory in the Social Sciences, and Market Structure and Behavior. Arranged by title.
      - Essays in Mathematical Economics in Honor of Oskar Morgenstern (1967), 1967-1968 and undated, (8 folders)
        - Proofs, notes, correspondence and book reviews. For additional reviews, see Box 40. (Box 73)
      - A Game Theoretical Approach to Political Economy, undated
        - Title cover sample. (Box 73)
          (Seems to have become Volume 2 of Game Theory in the Social Sciences.)
      - Game Theory (1964), 1963 and undated, (3 folders)
        - Proof and memorandum. Same as Game Theory and Related Approaches to To Social Behavior? (Box 74)
      - Game Theory and Related Approaches to Social Behavior (1964), 1962-1964 and undated, (1 box)
        - Notes, correspondence, reviews, revised manuscripts, galleys, reprint, advertisement. (Box 74-75)
      - Game Theory in the Social Sciences, Vols. 1 and 2 (1982, 1984), 1960-1984 and undated, (6 boxes)
        Game Theory in the Social Sciences includes materials that came to be published in a two-volume work, Game Theory and the Social Sciences (1982, 1984). Divided into roughly three groups related to project phases: (1) a small group of early notes and drafts from a joint project with Lloyd Shapley from the 1960s, with the intended title Competition, Welfare, and the Theory of Games; (2) a series of RAND working papers with Shapley from the early 1970s entitled Game Theory in Economics; and (3) drafts of the final book, authored by Shubik alone, from the 1970s and mid 1980s. For additional correspondence, see Box 37 and 38.
        - Competition, Welfare, and the Theory of Games, 1960s-1974 (Box 75)
          Folder houses outlines and drafts.
        - Game Theory in Economics (Box 75-76)
          Contains the drafts of five RAND working papers (also identified by chapter numbers) on game theory, authored by Shubik and Shapley: Introduction. The Use of Models; Decision Makers; The 'Rules of the Game'; Preferences and Utility; and Characteristic Function, Core, and Stable Set. Also contains the published working papers and associated correspondence. Chapter 5 materials are not present.
        - Game Theory in the Social Sciences (Box 76-80-A)
          Contains drafts and manuscripts of almost all chapters, appendices for Volumes 1 and 2; also houses drafts with editors' mark-ups, figures or illustrations, references, notes, related articles, research, reviews and some correspondence. Includes notes by Ed Paxson on Chapter 12. The last drafts in Box 80-A are stamped 20 March, 1984.
      - Market Structure and Behavior (1980), 1978-1984 and undated, (6 boxes)
        - Drafts (Box 81-83)
          Includes drafts (some with notes) for select chapters of Volume 1 and 2, with course packet, prospectus, correspondence. For additional correspondence, see Boxes 36 and 40.
        - Proofs (Box 84-85)
          Includes proofs of Volumes 1 and 2.
        - Research Materials (Box 85)
          Includes working papers, notes on various chapters, correspondence, scholarly articles by others, contents and references, research.
        - Typed Manuscripts (Box 85-86)
          Includes typed manuscripts for select chapters of Volume 1 and 2, includes an advertisement for the book
      - Mathematics of Conflict (1983), circa 1982, (3 folders)
        - Manuscript and royalty statement (Box 86)
      - Money and Financial Institutions (1999), undated, (1 folder)
        - Book cover sample (Box 86)
      - Political Economy, Oligopoly, and Experimental Games (1999), circa 1998, (1 folder)
        - Book cover sample (Box 87)
      - Readings in Game Theory, (1970-1978 and undated, (2 boxes) (Box 87-88)
        Includes materials for a book, edited by Garry Brewer and Martin Shubik, on readings in game theory, tentatively entitled Gaming and the Behavioral Sciences. Includes correspondence, research files, permissions, status reports and a few drafts. Does not appear to be published.
        - Permissions--addresses
          - Letters, part II, 1970-72
          - Letters, part III, 1970-76
          - Letters, part IV, 1970-72
          - Letters, not used, 1970-71
          - Status report
        - List of articles
          - No. 1, James Coleman, "In Defense of Games"
          - No. 2, Erving Goffman, "On Face Work"
          - No. 5, Cleo Cherryholmes, "Some Current Research on Effectiveness of Educational Simulations..."
          - No. 6, Sarane Boocock, "An Experimental Study Of the Learning Effects of Two Games with Simulated Environments"
          - No. 7, Michael Inbar, "The Differential Impact of a Game Simulating a Community Disaster"
          - No. 8, Richard Wing, "Two Computer-Based Economics Games for Sixth Graders"
          - No. 9, William Dill, "What Management Games Do Best"
          - No. 13, James McKenney and William Dill, "Influences on Learning in Simulation Games"
          - No. 41, Garry Brewer, "Summary Report of a Survey of Models, Simulations, and Games"
          - No. 52, Shubik and David Stern, "Some Experimental Non-Constant-Sum Games Revisited"
          - No 59, Shubik, "The Dollar Auction Game..."
          - "On the Scope of Gaming," 1971-72
          - Gaming and the Behavioral Sciences, Introduction and organization
          - Status report, 1970
          - Business files, 1972-78
      - Risk, Organizations, and Society (1991), 1970-1990 and undated, (3 boxes)
        Files house materials for a seminar taught by Shubik in 1987 at Yale, as well as other files on relevant topics and research into behavior and risk. Includes notes, correspondence, readings, and student papers. The lecture notes of featured seminar speakers were collected into a book entitled Risk, Organizations, and Society, published in 1991. Speakers include R. Abelson, J. Stolwijk among others.
        - Seminar (Box 88-89)
          Includes seminar outline, notes for select sessions, correspondence, miscellaneous readings, student papers.
          - Miscellaneous articles on risk, 1981-1989
          - Seminar outline
          - Session No. 1
          - Session No. 2, R. Abelson
          - Session No. 3
          - Session No. 4, Jan Stolwijk
          - Session No. 7, Brian Jenkins
          - Session No. 8, Thomas Schelling
          - Session No. 9, Homer Boynton
          - Session No. 11, Ernst Wynder
          - Session No. 12, Henry Kendall
          - Session No. 13, Alvin Weinberg
          - Correspondence with Alvin Weinberg
          - Seminar, miscellaneous readings
          - Seminar, student papers
        - Book (Box 89-90)
          Includes correspondence, review drafts, various revisions and proofs.
          - Correspondence with publishers
          - Contents
          - Drafts of Introduction, "Risk in a Complex World"
          - Review draft
          - Proofs
          - Chauncy Starr and Chris Whipple revisions
          - Henry Rowen revisions
          - Jenkins revisions
          - Boynton revisions
          - Schelling revisions
          - Weinberg revisions
          - Kendall revisions
      - Strategy and Market Structure (1959), 1955-1960 and undated, (11 folders)
        - Manuscript, reprints, correspondence, peer reviews, book reviews, and reprint permissions. (Box 90-91)
      - A Survey of Models, Simulations and Games, undated, (4 folders)
        - Manuscripts. Never published? (Box 91)
      - The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (1999), 1970-1999 and undated, (12 boxes)
        Subseries chiefly consists of materials associated with The Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (TMFI). Arranged in five parts: (1) papers and notes on the general topic of money and financial institutions; (2) an early draft of the project released piecemeal as Cowles Commission working papers (identified by the letter C, as in C-33); (3) drafts arranged chronologically; (4) manuscripts arranged chronologically; and (5) correspondence and book reviews. For additional correspondence, see Box 44.
        - Early Papers and Notes (Box 92-93)
          Files house early papers and research memoranda, RAND Working Papers, project planning and outlines.
          - A Theory of Money and Banking in a General Equilibrium System, Research Memorandum, Institut Für Höhere Studien und Wissenschaftliche Forschung Wien, 1970
          - Theory of Money, Prices and the Rate of Interest I, RAND Working Paper, 1971
          - Theory of Money, Prices and the Rate of Interest III, RAND Working Paper, 1971
          - Bankruptcy and Efficiency in a General Equilibrium Model with Incomplete Markets
          - An Informal Guide to Some Papers on a Theory of Money and Financial Institutions, 1974-1982
          - A Strategic Market Game with Seigniorage Costs of Fiat Money, 1992
          - National Science Foundation proposal
        - Early Cowles Foundation Reports (TMFI-related)
          Includes bound CFDPs and working papers.
          - "Measurable, Transferable, Comparable Utility and Money," C-1
          - "The Missing Degree of Freedom," TMFI part III
          - "Some Informal Notes, Preliminary Results, and Models Relevant to Dynamic Monetary Economies," C-12, TMFI part X
          - "Some Problems and Conjectures...," C-25, TMFI part XIX
          - "A Linear Exchange Model with Financial Institutions, TMFI part XX
          - "A Price-Quantity Buy-Sell Market," TMFI part XXII
          - "Beyond General Equilibrium," C-31, TMFI part XXVII
          - "The Optimal Bankruptcy Rule," C-33, TMFI part XXX, 1976
          - "A Closed Economic System with Production and Exchange...," C-34
          - Notes and Drafts, C-35
          - "Banks, Insurance, and Financial Markets," C-36, TMFI part 31
          - "On the Market Value of Information," C-39, TMFI part 33
          - "A Multiperiod Trading Economy," C-40, TMFI part 34
          - "Bankruptcy and Optimality in a Closed Trading Economy," TMFI part 35
          - Miscellaneous notes and drafts
        - TMFI Drafts (Box 93-97)
          - Drafts (some handwritten) of most chapters of both volumes, with notes, appendices and MIT draft copy.
        - TMFI Manuscripts (Box 98-103)
          - Manuscripts for TMFI, including such groupings as "Master Set," typed manuscripts, marked-up manuscripts, proofs, revised proofs and bound copies of TMFI (for purposes such as seminars).
        - Correspondence and Book Reviews, 3 folders (Box 103)
          - Two pieces of correspondence and several reviews.
      - Other Books by Shubik or with Writings by Shubik, (5 items) (Box 115)
        Single volumes of published books, with no manuscript materials. Arranged by title.
        - La Décision: Agrégation et dynamique des orderes de préférence, Aix-en-Provence 3 - 7 juillet 1967 (1969, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, Paris)
          Papers and concluding remarks by Shubik.
        - Games for Society, Business and War: Towards a Theory of Gaming (1975, Elsevier)
        - Uses and Methods of Gaming (1975, Elsevier), (2 copies)
        - Wirtschafts-und Sozialwissenschaften zwischen Theorie und Praxis: 30 Jahre Institut für Höhere Studien in Wien (1993, Physica Verlag)
      - Miscellaneous Book Reviews, (1 folder) (Box 103)
        - Includes book reviews not associated with major works in this collection.
      - Unpublished Works, (8 folders)
        Includes numerous unpublished works by Shubik. Titles include such works as Behavior, Society and Nuclear War and The War Game. Materials consist of manuscripts, correspondence, outlines and out takes. Arranged alphabetically by title.
        - Behavior, Society and Nuclear War, Vol. II (unpublished chapter, correspondence) (Box 104)
        - The Economics of Competitive Strategy (outline of chapters, unfinished, with Forman, L. and Naylor, T.)
        - Game Theory (unpublished manuscript), (2 folders)
        - Microeconomic Analysis, (unpublished manuscript), (2 folders)
        - The War Game (outline, out takes), (2 folders)
      - Unidentified Publications, (20 folders)
        Included in this subseries are chapters, secondary sources, models and figures for works that could not be identified with a specific work. The files often include correspondence and working papers. Arranged alphabetically by title.
        - Corporate Control, Efficient Markets... (working papers, correspondence) (Box 104)
        - Diagrams and figures from Volume II
        - Entry and exit growth (Chapter 8, handwritten draft)
        - Figures and tables for various publications (Box 105)
        - Drawings and manuscripts on game theory
        - Mathematical institutional economics and oligopoly theory (typed draft for Chapter 13 of unidentified work)
        - N-Person Games (chapters for an unidentified publication), 1963, (2 folders)
        - Prices, Production, Advertising, and the Goals of the Firm (typed draft for Chapter 6 of unidentified book)
        - Probability/consumption models, undated
        - Secondary sources for "6" (includes articles by R. Rosenthal and others)
        - Secondary sources for "6.2.2" (includes articles by E. Zabel and Y. Plessner)
        - Secondary sources for "6.3" (includes articles by L. Telser and others)
        - Secondary sources for "14" (includes articles by B. Shitovitz and others)
        - Sequential Optimization (various notes for Chapter 4)
        - Social Policy and Control... (draft for Chapter 14)
        - A Static Theory of Cooperative or Collusive Action (manuscript of Chapter 8) (Box 106)
        - Strategic Audit (material for Chapter 14, including working papers and article)
        - Trade Practice Rules (secondary sources for unidentified Chapter 15)
        - Urban Systems Gaming (secondary sources for "14")
    - Other Papers Subseries, 1951-2005 and undated, (6 boxes)
      Here are works that are not listed in Shubik's numeric bibliography. The files often include such material as manuscripts, reprints, drafts, correspondence, proofs and working papers. Arranged alphabetically by title.
      - Accepting Orders for a Job Shop... (typed manuscript), 1957 (Box 106)
      - Accounting and Economic Theory (manuscript, correspondence, referee reports), 2003
      - Accounting Theory and its Relationship to General Equilibrium Theory (typed manuscript), 1992
      - Adam Crusoe's GNP, Welfare and Money Supply (typed manuscript), undated
      - The Analysis of Nuclear Stability in a Multipolar World with Bracken, J. and Quint, T., 1993
      - Applied General Equilibrium Computations and Strategic Market Games with Rutherford, T. (draft with revisions), undated
      - Auctions, Bidding and Contracting (manuscript), undated
      - Babylonian Economics Exhibit (correspondence with Haloo, W.), 2000
      - Barrons (letter to the editor), 1983
      - Bertrand, Joseph (New Palgrave entry), 1985
      - A Biographical Model of Migration (drafts with revisions), 1994
      - Birth Processes and Intergenerational Transfers with Arthur, W., undated
      - Book Reviews by Shubik, (2 folders)
      - Book Reviews of Gaming Literature and Allied Topics with Brewer, G. (RAND typed manuscript), 1971
      - Budgets in a Decentralized Organization with Incomplete Information (RAND typed manuscript), 1970
      - Capital Markets, Efficiency and Corporate Control (proof), undated
      - Center for Competitive and Conflict Systems, Report #8 (typed manuscript), 1984-1985 (Box 107)
      - On Coalition Games (ISAC working paper), undated
      - A Comparison of Six Simple Models of Production and Exchange with Sahi, S. (draft), undated
      - A Comparison between some Features of a Purely Competitive Market (typed manuscript), 1956
      - Competition or Cooperation on NASDAQ (typed manuscript), 1996
      - The Competitive Equilibrium of a Direct Market and Core with Shapley, L. (handwritten drafts), undated
      - The Computation of Equilibria in Monetary Economies with Quint, T and Rutherford, T. (manuscript), 1995
      - Containing Cost Growth in Defense Procurement (typed manuscript), undated
      - Control of Dividends, Capital Subscriptions, and Physical Inventories with Li, Lode, Sobel (copy of latest draft), 2003
      - Cooperative Games (correspondence), 1985
      - Corporate Control, Efficient Markets, the Public Good, the Law and Economic Theory (handwritten drafts), undated
      - Corporate Reality and Accounting for Investors with Whitman, M (reprint, notes, correspondence), 1972
      - Costly Search, Local Maxima and Matrix Games with Lee, J., 1993
      - Cournot, Antoine Augustin (draft, notes for The New Palgrave), 1985
      - Crisis Stability Games with Bracken, J. (working paper), 1990
      - The Defense Implications of the Recent and Future Changes in the World... with Slighton, R. (typed outline, drafts), 1997, (2 folders)
      - The Demand for a New Consumer Durable: some models (typed manuscript with revisions), undated
      - Design for Forecasting (typed manuscript), 1957
      - Development: Models, Simulations, and Games (draft), 1970
      - A Dynamic Strategic Market Game with Limited Borrowing... (draft with notes), 1982
      - Economic Consequences of Missile Defense with Bracken, P. (correspondence, drafts), 2001
      - Fiat Money in a Mass Market with Whitt, W. (handwritten draft), 1971-1972
      - On Fiduciary Risk and Decision-making (typed manuscript with revisions), undated
      - Financial Systems: Instabilities and Conflict (working paper), 1995
      - Financing Trade and the Price Level... (drafts), 1994
      - A Fond Remembrance of Per Bax (reprint), 2002
      - On the Future Role of the Corporation (manuscript), 2000
      - A Game Theoretic Approach to the Theory of Money... (conference paper), 1988 (Box 108)
      - Game Theory (CFP paper), undated
      - Games of Status and Wealth and Status... (typed manuscript), 1996-1997
      - Game Theory: The Language of Strategy (working paper), 1981
      - Game Theory and Operations Research: Some Musings 50 Years Later (reprint), 2002
      - Game Theory and Operations Research Sixty Years Later (handwritten draft), undated
      - Game Theory and Princeton (CFPP), undated
      - Gaming (manuscript), 1993
      - Gaming Literature Review with Brewer, G., Savage, E. (typed manuscript), 1971, (2 folders)
      - An Infinite Horizon Strategic Market Game with Fiat Money, Part II with Karatzas, I and Sudderth, W. (working paper), 1992
      - An Informal Guide to Some Papers of a Theory of Money and Financial Institutions (research memorandum), 1977
      - Information, Theories of Competition and Theory of Games (draft), 1951
      - Intergenerational Political Economy (drafts), 1980
      - Involved Parties, Incentives and Process (typed manuscript, correspondence), 1976
      - Kohlberg's Critique of Perfect Equilibrium (drafts), undated
      - The Literature of Gaming, Simulation, and Model Building (drafts, revisions), 1972
      - On Local and Network Games with Quint, T. (drafts), 2003
      - The Marginal Value of a Player (typed manuscript), undated
      - Market Share, Competition among Firms... with Bak, P. Maslov, S., Karatzas, Y, Sudderth, W. (manuscript, correspondence), 1996
      - Mathematical Economics (draft), 1986
      - Model of Strategic Behavior and Nuclear Deterrence (correspondence), 1992
      - Money and the Monetization of Credit (revised proof), undated
      - Money as an Asset and the Role of Clearing Houses (handwritten draft with manuscripts), 1995 (Box 109)
      - Money as Insurance (drafts), 1983
      - The Names of the Games with Powers, I. and Yeung, I. (discussion paper, correspondence), 1990
      - Normative Estimates about how to Settle Three Person Cooperative Games (working paper), 1991
      - A Note on Budget Allocation Games without Side Payments (handwritten draft), 1996
      - A Note on the Egalitarian Selection of a Competitive Equilibrium... (typed manuscript), 1983
      - A Note on Paper Gold (typed draft with revisions), undated
      - A Note on the Relationship between the Value and the Competitive Equilibrium (typed manuscripts), undated
      - A Note on the Unique Minimal Loan Equilibrium in an Exchange Economy (CFPP), undated
      - Notes of the Business Game, 1972 Data (typed draft), 1983
      - Notes on an Experimental Evaluation of Four Leading Delicatessens with Madansky, A (typed manuscript, correspondence), 1976
      - Observations on the Vietnam War (draft), 1968
      - An OLG Economy with Stochastic Individual Income, Part I with Karatzas, I. and Sudderth, W. (typed draft), 1999
      - The One Bid Bargain (working paper), undated
      - A One Period Exchange Economy with a Mutual Band and Redemption in Gold (typed draft), 1990
      - Oskar Morgenstern (typed draft), undated
      - Paper Gold (draft), undated
      - Phylax (editor letter), 1988-1991
      - The Playing of a Simple Extensive Form Game (working paper), 1991
      - The Price for the Widow's Cruise (draft), undated
      - On Production and Growth (typed manuscript, revisions), undated
      - Production with Dividend and Bankruptcy Penalties with Sobel, Li (paper, correspondence), 1993
      - A Program in the Study of Dynamic Monetary Economies (typed manuscript, drafts), 1991
      - Quantity Variation Oligopoly with Fouraker, L., Siegel, S. (typed manuscript), undated
      - RAND Corporation Reports with Dalkey, N. and Brewer, G., 1968-1971
      - Rational or Irrational Threats (manuscript), undated (Box 110)
      - Risk Aversion, Fiduciary Relationships... (abstract), undated
      - The Santa Fe Art Market (typed draft, revisions, manuscript), 1992
      - On Sensitivity Analysis, Economic Models... (handwritten draft), 1972
      - The Social Function and Economic Future of the Art Museum with Baumol, W. (study and book proposal), 1986-1989
      - Some Musings of Gaming and Simulation (typed manuscript), 1993
      - Some Unresolved Problems in Mathematical Economics... (draft), undated
      - On the Stages of Innovation (manuscript), 1995
      - A Strategic Market Game with Limited Borrowing and Exogenous Uncertainty (typed draft), 1982
      - Strategic Market Games and Market Mechanisms (handwritten draft), undated
      - Theory of Bidding with Griesmer, J., Morrison, H. (revised paper with notes), undated
      - A Theory of Money and Banking in a General Equilibrium System (research memorandum, notes), 1970